<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PhytoKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">PhytoKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">PhytoKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1314-2011</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1314-2003</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/phytokeys.21.5213</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Reinterpretation of the nomenclatural type of 
                    <italic>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</italic> (Malvaceae, Bombacoideae) reveals an overlooked new species from Bolivia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Carvalho-Sobrinho</surname>
                        <given-names>Jefferson G. de</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Queiroz</surname>
                        <given-names>Luciano P. de</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Alverson</surname>
                        <given-names>William S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Herbário HUEFS, Universidade Estadual de Feira de Santana, Avenida Transnordestina s/n, Novo Horizonte, 44036-900, Feira de Santana, Bahia, Brazil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Botany, Birge Hall, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 53706, Madison, WI, U.S.A. 
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Jefferson G. de Carvalho-Sobrinho (<email xlink:type="simple">jef.sobrinho@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Laurence J. Dorr</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>9</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>21</issue>
            <fpage>53</fpage>
            <lpage>61</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>26</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jefferson G. de Carvalho-Sobrinho, Luciano P. de Queiroz, William S. Alverson</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>In the course of a taxonomic revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dugand, one of us (JGCS) frequently has observed herbarium specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name> that comprise a mixture of different Angiosperm families. In particular, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kuntze) A. Robyns, a frequent name in checklists of the Bolivian flora, is based on type material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuntze that is clearly a mixture of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> flowers and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tabebuia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gomes ex DC. (<tp:taxon-name>Bignoniaceae</tp:taxon-name>) leaves. We herein designate as the lectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> the flowers of an herbarium sheet deposited in NY and as epitype a complete specimen (leaves, flowers, and fruit) in HUEFS. We consider <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be a synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mart.) A. Robyns, a species widespread in Neotropical seasonally dry forest of Bolivia, Brazil, Paraguay, and Peru. Furthermore, we describe a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carv.-Sobr., apparently endemic to seasonally dry tropical forest (SDTF) in Bolivia (Chiquitano dry forest), based on specimens commonly but incorrectly identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic>.We also comment on the morphology, distribution, and conservation status of this new species.</p>
            </abstract>
            <trans-abstract xml:lang="es">
                <label>Resumen</label>
                <p>En el curso de una revisión taxonómica de <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dugand, uno de nosotros (JGCS) con frecuencia se ha observado especímenes de herbario de <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name> que comprenden una mezcla de diferentes familias de angiospermas. En particular, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kuntze) A.Robyns, un nombre frecuente en las listas de la flora boliviana, se basa en el material tipo de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuntze que es claramente una mezcla de flores de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> y hojas de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tabebuia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gomes ex DC. (<tp:taxon-name>Bignoniaceae</tp:taxon-name>). Aquí se designa como el lectotipo de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> las flores de uno espécimen de el herbario NY y como epitipo uno espécimen completo (hojas, flores y frutos) de el herbario HUEFS. Consideramos <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> como sinónimo de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mart.) A.Robyns, una especie ampliamente distribuida en los bosques neotropicales estacionalmente seco de Bolivia, Brasil, Paraguay y Perú. Por otra parte, se describe una especie nueva, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carv.-Sobr., aparentemente endémica de los Bosques secos Chiquitanos en Bolivia, con base en colecciones comúnmente, pero incorrectamente identificado, como <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, con comentarios sobre su morfología, distribución y estado de conservación.</p>
            </trans-abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Bombax</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Chiquitano dry forest</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>seasonally dry neotropical forest</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Tabebuia</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>typification</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In his revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> L. <italic>s.l</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Robyns (1963)</xref> transferred <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuntze to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dugand and considered <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kuntze) A.Robyns to be endemic to Bolivia. Based solely on the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Kuntze s.n</tp:taxon-name></italic>., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), Robyns described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> as having long petiolules and scarcely expanded petiole apices. In his key to the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic>, he used these two characters to separate this speciesfrom morphologically closely related congeners. According to Robyns’s description, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> also has grooved (canaliculate) petiolules, which if true would represent a unique character in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Photograph of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuntze (NY 133522).</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="PhytoKeys-021-053-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>In the course of a taxonomic revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Carvalho-Sobrinho, in prep.), mixed collections of <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name>, including type specimens based on mixtures, often have been observed. This is especially common for collections from seasonally dry Neotropical forest habitats where species often are leafless during the flowering period. In the present case, a careful examination of the morphology of the leaves and flowers of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> revealed that the specimen is a mixture of reproductive and vegetative elements from two different Angiosperm families. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Robyns (1963)</xref> failed to note that his type specimen has leaflets that are articulated with the petiole, a character state unknown in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic>; the genus is separated from all other <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name> by the synapomorphy of non-articulated leaflets, which lack an abscission zone between the apex of the petiole and the base of the petiolules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Robyns 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Carvalho-Sobrinho and Queiroz 2011</xref>).</p>
            <p>The holotype of <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (NY) and an image of an isotype (B as F negative 9535; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Field Museum 2012</xref>) show floral material matching that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mart.) A.Robyns, including an androecium with a glabrous, relatively long staminal tube, filaments freely originating from the apex of the tube (i.e., without phalanges), and typical hippocrepiform anthers. However, the vegetative material of these two type specimensmatches the leaves of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tabebuia aurea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Silva Manso) Benth. &amp; Hook. f. ex S. Moore (<tp:taxon-name>Bignoniaceae</tp:taxon-name>), with suberous branches, opposite leaves (inferred from leaf scars), longer and grooved petiolules, leaflets with a clear abscission zone, and a clearly different venation pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a <!--PageBreak-->species widespread in Neotropical seasonally dry forest of Bolivia, Brazil, Paraguay, and Peru, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tabebuia aurea</tp:taxon-name></italic> are sympatric in the Bolivian Chiquitano dry forest and the latter species has been collected several times in the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (municipality of Velasco, Santa Cruz, Bolivia) according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Tropicos (2012)</xref> and specimen labels from herbaria (F, US, and WIS).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Lectotypification of Bombax heteromorphum">
            <title>Lectotypification of <italic>Bombax heteromorphum</italic></title>
            <p>Having demonstrated above that the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> represents a mixture of leaves belonging to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tabebuia aurea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and detached flowers belonging to a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> it becomes necessary to select a lectotype from these two elements in order to fix the application of the name (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">McNeill et al. 2012</xref>, Art. 9.14). We choose to lectotypify the name on the flowers only because the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> always has been associated with <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold> (Mart.) A. Robyns, Bull. Jard. Bot. État Bruxelles 33: 57. 1963.</p>
            <p>= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuntze, Revis. Gen. Pl. 3 (3): 18. 1898. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kuntze) A.Robyns, Bull. Jard. Bot. État Bruxelles 33: 80. 1963. <bold>Lectotype (designated here)</bold>: BOLIVIA. Velasco, <italic>O.Kuntze s.n</italic>. (NY flowers only!). <bold>Epitype (designated here):</bold> BRAZIL. Bahia, Inhaúmas, ca. 10 km de Inhaúmas na estrada para Santa Maria da Vitória, Cerrado, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">13°13'47&quot;S, 44°33'09&quot;W</named-content>, 600 m alt., 15 Aug 2005, <italic>Carvalho-Sobrinho &amp; Queiroz 577</italic> (HUEFS 100549!, lf, fl, fr, in two sheets).</p>
            <sec sec-type="A new species of Pseudobombax long confused with P. heteromorphum">
                <title>A new species of <italic>Pseudobombax</italic> long confused with <italic>P. heteromorphum</italic></title>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Robyns (1963)</xref> and subsequent authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Killeen et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Jardim et al. 2003</xref>) assigned specimens of a distinctive Bolivian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic> to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax heteromorphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> in error. These collections in fact represent a new species, which we describe here.</p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pulchellum</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77128380-1</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Pseudobombax_pulchellum</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Carv.–Sobr.</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">, 3</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Similar to <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mart.) A.Robyns by its long petiolules, obovate to suborbicular leaflets, and maculate seeds, but differing by the smaller leaves, flowers and fruits, slender branches, petioles 4 times the length of the petiolules (vs. a petiole/petiolule ratio of 6–12 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and fruits acuminate for the distal 20% of their length (vs. 3%–5% in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type">
                        <title>Type.</title>
                        <p>BOLIVIA. Santa Cruz: 42 km E of Curuyuqui, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°45'56&quot;S, 62°13'59&quot;W</named-content>, 350 m, 25 October 1991 (lf, fr), <italic>A. Gentry, R. Foster &amp; M. Peña 75227</italic> (holotype: MO!; isotypes: F!, LPB!, USZ!, WIS!).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Treelets3–8 m, deciduous; branches glabrous, relatively slender, often covered with pale wax; brachyblasts absent. Stipules not seen. Leaves palmately compound, clustered at apex of the branches; petioles (17–) 34–87 mm long, flattened, slender, glabrous, usually glaucous with pale wax at the ends, bases slightly thickened, apices slightly thickened to 3–4 mm diam.; petiolules 14–22 mm long; leaflets (4) 5 (7), chartaceous, proximal leaflets 17–38 × 9–30 mm, distal leaflets 45–57 (–75) × 29–51 mm, obovate, broadly elliptic to suborbicular, apices retuse, rarely acuminate, bases obtuse, rounded, truncate to slightly cordate, margins entire, glabrous on both surfaces, except for sparse, peltate microtrichomes, abaxial surface dull-brown in dried state, midrib prominent abaxially, 8–12 secondary veins inconspicuous, intersecondary veins present, tertiary veins reticulate. Complete inflorescences not seen; pedicels 19 mm long (–26 mm when in fruit). Flowers c. 65 mm long; receptacle with single whorl of c. 5 glands; calyces 8–9 × 11–15 mm, cupular to campanulate, truncate, outwardly glabrous except for peltate microtrichomes, internally sericeous; petals (50–) 61–70 × 6–8 mm, linear to lanceolate, apex acute, dark-brown externally, covered with tufted, rigid hairs, inwardly pilose to glabrescent towards the base, covered mainly by verrucose microtrichomes; stamens c. 150–200, staminal tube 9–10 × 4 mm, pubescent, phalanges absent, filaments free for 40–58 mm, anthers hippocrepiform c. 2 mm long; ovary 5 × 2 mm, oblong-obovoid, glabrous except for peltate microtrichomes, style c. 70 mm long, glabrous, stigma inconspicuously 5-lobed. Capsules c. 90 mm long, woody, oblong-obovoid, conspicuously acuminate for distal 15 mm or so, valves coriaceous, glabrous, kapok abundant, golden brown. Seeds c. 5 mm diam., subglobose to pyriform, maculate, glabrous.</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p>Photograph of an isotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carv.-Sobr. (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Gentry</tp:taxon-name></italic> et al.75227, F 2111431).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="PhytoKeys-021-053-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p>Distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carv.-Sobr. in Santa Cruz, Bolivia. Dashed lines indicate the boundaries of the Kaa-Iya del Gran Chaco National Park.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="PhytoKeys-021-053-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from only four sites in the Department of Santa Cruz, Bolivia, and appears to be endemic to Chiquitano dry forest at elevations of 230 to 520 m.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Phenology">
                        <title>Phenology.</title>
                        <p>Flowers of this new species are known from a single collection made in June; fruiting material was collected in October.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet refers to the small, delicate leaflets and long, slender petiolules of this species, diagnostic even in sterile specimens. The epithet also honors the Brazilian botanist Aline Costa da Mota for her important insights and collaboration on the systematics of <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>Although <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurs in the Kaa-Iya del Gran Chaco National Park, itmust be considered Near Threatened because it is known from only four sites and “there are plausible events that may cause the species to decline, but these are unlikely to make the species Extinct or Critically Endangered in a short time” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">IUCN 2010</xref>). Extensive fieldwork in other areas of dry forests in Bolivia is necessary to properly survey and to assess the status of this species.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Specimens examined">
                        <title>Specimens examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>BOLIVIA. Santa Cruz</bold>: Chiquitos, 19–23 Dec 1993 (fr), <italic>G. Navarro Sanchez 2192</italic> (LPB!); Cordillera, 09 January 1993 (lf), <italic>G. Navarro Sanchez 1713</italic> (MO!, USZ!); <italic>ibidem</italic>, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°29'20&quot;S, 61°07'06&quot;W</named-content>, 230 m, 17 June 1998 (fl), <italic>Alfredo F. Fuentes &amp; G. Navarro Sanchez 2436</italic> (MO!); Ñuflo de Chavez, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">17°05'00&quot;S, 61°47'00&quot;W</named-content>, 400 m, 24 October 1995 (lf), <italic>Alfredo F. Fuentes 1132</italic> (LPB!, USZ,WIS!).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                        <title>Discussion.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a remarkable species by its diminutive aspect, especially the relatively small, retuse, obovate to suborbicular leaflets, and the flowers; the petiolules are markedly long in relation to the petiole, and fruits are conspicuously acuminate. It seems to be closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mart.) A. Robyns, a sympatric congener in Bolivian Chiquitano dry forest. The two are similar because of their glabrous aspect, long petiolules, leaflets with retuse apices, truncate to cordate bases, and maculate seeds.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->The new species is also similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax croizatii</tp:taxon-name></italic> A.Robyns and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax minimum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carv.-Sobr. &amp; L.P. Queiroz; both of these species share small flowers (60–65 mm long), glabrous staminal tubes, androecia with relatively few stamens (c. 150–200), and glabrous fruits. The following key can be used to separate these four species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petiolules 14–75 mm long. Petals externally blackish, staminal tube lacking phalanges (filaments freely originating from the apex of the tube). Seeds bicolored, maculate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petiolules to 5 mm long. Petals externally cream-colored, staminal tube originating phalanges 3–5 mm long. Seeds uniformly colored</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petioles 4 times the length of the petiolules. Flowers c. 65 mm long, calyx 8–9 mm long, staminal tube c. 10 mm long. Capsules c. 90 mm long, acuminate for the distal 20% of their length</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax pulchellum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bolivia)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petioles 6–12 times the length of the petiolules. Flowers 15–22 mm long, calyx 15–25 mm long, staminal tube 35–60 mm long. Capsules 14–24 mm long, acuminate for the distal 3%–5% of their length</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax longiflorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bolivia, Brazil, Paraguay, Peru)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaflets 7–9, obovate, cuneate, margins revolute. Flowers to 60 mm long, staminal tube glabrous. Capsules 55 mm long, not acuminate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax minimum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Central Brazil)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaflets 5, elliptic to broad-elliptic, acute, margins plane. Flowers 85–100 mm long, staminal tube with bands of simple trichomes. Capsules c. 70 mm long, acuminate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudobombax croizatii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Colombia, Venezuela)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Thanks are due Hibert Huaylla for photographs of <tp:taxon-name>Bombacoideae</tp:taxon-name> specimens from Bolivia; the staff and curators of F (especially Nancy Hensold and Robin Foster), LPB, MO, NY, and WIS for scanned images; the reviewers and the subject editor for their suggestions to the manuscript; the Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado da Bahia (process APP0006/2011) and the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico–CNPq (processes 300811/2010-1 and 563546/2010-7-REFLORA) for financial support. This paper is part of the PhD thesis of JGCS prepared in the Programa de Pós-Graduação em Botânica (PPGBot-UEFS) and supported by a grant from the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior–CAPES.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho-Sobrinho</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Queiroz</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Morphological cladistic analysis of <italic>Pseudobombax</italic> Dugand (Malvaceae,Bombacoideae) and allied genera.</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Botânica</source> <volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0100-84042011000200007" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/S0100-84042011000200007</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>Museum</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Image of isotype <italic>Bombax heteromorphum</italic>, photographed by F. MacBride at the Berlin Herbarium. Berlin Negatives, Botany Collections Database. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emuweb.fieldmuseum.org/botany/berDisplay.php?irn=243333&amp;QueryPage=%2Fbotany%2Fsearch_berlin.php" xlink:type="simple">http://emuweb.fieldmuseum.org/botany/berDisplay.php?irn=243333&amp;QueryPage=%2Fbotany%2Fsearch_berlin.php</ext-link>. The Field Museum, Chicago, IL. [accessed 31.12.2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>IUCN</surname> <given-names>Standards and Petitions Subcommittee</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Guidelines for Using the IUCN Red List Categories and Criteria. Version 8.1. Prepared by the Standards and Petitions Subcommittee in March 2010. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://intranet.iucn.org/webfiles/doc/SSC/RedList/RedListGuidelines.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://intranet.iucn.org/webfiles/doc/SSC/RedList/RedListGuidelines.pdf</ext-link> [accessed 09.10.2011]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jardim</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killeen</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Guia de los Arboles y Arbustos del Bosque Seco Chiquitano, Bolivia. Missouri Botanical Garden Press. 324p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Killeen</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>Guía de árboles de Bolivia. Missouri Botanical Garden and Herbario Nacional de Bolivia, St. Louis, MO and La Paz. 958p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrie</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname> <given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demoulin</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greuter</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawksworth</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herendeen</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marhold</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prado</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prud´Homme</surname> <given-names>van Reine WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiersema</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turland</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) (<year>2012</year>) <source>International Code of Nomenclature for Algae, Fungi, and Plants (Melbourne Code): adopted by the Eighteenth International Botanical Congress Melbourne, Australia, July 2011. Regnum Vegetabile 154. Koeltz Scientific Books. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iapt-taxon.org/nomen/main.php" xlink:type="simple">http://www.iapt-taxon.org/nomen/main.php</ext-link> [accessed 03.05.2013]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Robyns</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Essai de monographie du genre <italic>Bombax</italic> s.l. (Bombacaceae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin du Jardin Botanique de l’État à Bruxelles</source> <volume>33</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>) ): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>315</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tropicos</surname> <given-names></given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Tropicos.org. Missouri Botanical Garden. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tropicos.org/Name/3701652" xlink:type="simple">http://www.tropicos.org/Name/3701652</ext-link> [accessed 18.10.2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>