<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PhytoKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/phytokeys.2.731</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title> Trichospermum lessertianum comb. n., the correct name for the Cuban species of richospermum (Malvaceae, Grewioideae)  also found in Mexico and Central America
                </article-title>
            </title-group>	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Dorr</surname>
                        <given-names>Laurence J.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Department of Botany, National Museum of Natural History, MRC–166, Smithsonian Institution, P.O. Box 37012, Washington, D.C. 20013–7012, U.S.A.</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding authors: Laurence J. Dorr (<email xlink:type="simple">dorrl@si.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Hanno Schaefer</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>2</issue>
            <fpage>17</fpage>
            <lpage>22</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>4</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Laurence J. Dorr</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>            
            <abstract>            	
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The correct name for the Cuban species of <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name> Bl. (<tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Grewioideae</tp:taxon-name>) also found in Mexico and Central America is <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum lessertianum</tp:taxon-name> (Hochr.) Dorr, <bold>comb. n.</bold> The name <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum mexicanum</tp:taxon-name> (DC.) Baill., incorrectly applied to this Cuban species, should be restricted to a species endemic to western and southern Mexico.</p>
            </abstract>	
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Belotia</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Cuba</kwd>
                <kwd>Grewioideae</kwd>
                <kwd>Malvaceae</kwd>
                <kwd>Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>new combination</kwd>
                <kwd>Tiliaceae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Trichospermum</italic></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name> Bl. (<tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Grewioideae</tp:taxon-name>, or <tp:taxon-name>Tiliaceae</tp:taxon-name>) is a genus of ca. 40 species found in tropical America, Asia, and the Pacific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kostermans 1962</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1972</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> A. Rich., a generic synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name>, was described from Cuba. Misinterpretations of the legitimacy and identity of its generitype, <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> A. Rich., have led authors treating <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name> (or <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name>) for various floras and revisions to adopt species names that are incorrect. Sorting out this confusion requires determining where <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> was first published (there are three competing publications); demonstrating that <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> was <!--PageBreak-->nomenclaturally superfluous when published; and establishing the identity of the name, <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> DC., that should have been adopted as the generitype of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>Achille Richard published <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> in three different works that appeared in the 1840s; in volume 10 of Ramón de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia física, política y natural de la isla de Cuba</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Richard 1845</xref>: 82; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan 1983</xref>: no. 10.000), in an unnumbered volume of a French edition of the same work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Richard 1841</xref>: 207; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan 1983</xref>: nos. 9150, 10.002), and in the second volume of Charles d’Orbigny’s <italic>Dictionnaire universel d’histoire naturelle</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Richard 1842</xref>: 539; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Stafleu and Cowan 1981</xref>: no. 7096; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Evenhuis 1990</xref>). The volumes of the French version of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic>, at least, were issued in parts (livraisons) and these parts were distributed well before the publication dates given on the volumes as a whole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Brizicky 1962</xref>: 84–86; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan 1983</xref>: no. 9150). While the title pages of both the French and Spanish volumes of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic> that include <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> have the year 1845, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Brizicky (1962: 84–86)</xref> determined that the description of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> in the French edition actually appeared in a part (livraison) issued in 1841. The strongest evidence for this is the review of Richard’s contribution to Cuban botany published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Grisebach (1842)</xref>, which established that the livraison containing <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> was available by the end of 1841. This is the publication date accepted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan (1983: nos. 9150, 10.002)</xref>. The publication of the second volume of d’Orbigny’s <italic>Dictionnaire</italic>, which included a description of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name>, followed in 1842. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Stafleu and Cowan (1981: no. 7096)</xref> dated this volume 30 July 1842, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Evenhuis (1990)</xref> subsequently presented evidence that 20 June 1842 is the latest date at which the livraison containing a description of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> could have appeared. (The earliest possible, but not probable, date for the publication of this livraison is 24 January 1842). The description of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> in the <italic>Dictionnaire</italic> cites the paging and plate number (albeit incorrect) of the Spanish edition of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic>, which implies that the latter was typeset but presumably not yet distributed. No other evidence has surfaced indicating that the publication of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> in the Spanish edition of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic> was earlier than the date on the title page (i.e., 1845; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan 1983</xref>: no. 10.000) and without proof establishing some other date, the one appearing in the printed matter must be accepted as correct (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McNeill et al. 2006</xref>: Art. 31.1).</p>
            <p>The fact that <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name> was first published in the French edition of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic> has nomenclatural implications for the legitimacy of its generitype, <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name>. In the French edition, <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Richard 1841</xref>: 209) is a superfluous renaming of <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> DC. (1824: 510) as the latter name was placed in synonymy and is the name that should have been adopted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McNeill et al. 2006</xref>: Art. 52). Later, in both d’Orbigny’s <italic>Dictionnaire</italic> and in the Spanish edition of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic>, Richard equivocated with respect to this synonymy. In the former instance, he (1842: 540) wrote “<tp:taxon-name>Belotia greviæfolia</tp:taxon-name> Rich. (<italic>Fl. Cubens</italic> p. 82, t. 22), qui est probablement le <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> DC.” and in the latter (1845: 83) he cited <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> in synonymy with a question mark. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Sprague (1921)</xref>, who revised the genus <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name>, recognized that the Mexican and Cuban species differed, but he failed to appreciate that <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> was an illegitimate name and he used this name for one of two species he recognized from Cuba. He also confused <tp:taxon-name>Belotia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> (DC.) K. Schum.<!--PageBreak--> (basionym <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name>) with yet a different species occurring in Mexico and Central America. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bullock (1939)</xref> continued to use the illegitimate name <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> for a species from Cuba, but expanded his concept of this taxon’s range to include Central America. He also continued to confuse the identity of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia mexicana</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Farr et al. (1979: 91)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rodríguez Fuentes (2000: 31)</xref> began to clarify the nomenclatural confusion by recognizing that <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> is illegitimate, but the former did so while citing a place of publication (d’Orbigny’s <italic>Dictionnaire</italic>) that if in fact had been the earliest publication would have resulted in the legitimate publication of the name (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McNeill et al. 2006</xref>: Art. 52, Note 1, Ex. 12) and the latter although citing the earliest place of publication failed to realize that <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> is not conspecific with the Cuban species of <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>Although the plate accompanying the description of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> is numbered tab. 21, the protologues of both Spanish and French versions of de la Sagra’s <italic>Historia</italic> incorrectly cite tab. 22, which is a plate illustrating <tp:taxon-name>Triumfetta grossulariifolia</tp:taxon-name> A. Rich. (<tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Grewioideae</tp:taxon-name>). The plate caption for <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> in the French (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Richard 1841</xref>: 211), but not the Spanish version (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Richard 1845</xref>: 84), however, is correctly labeled tab. 21. Although the plates today invariably are bound separately from the text in a folio volume, text and plates originally were probably available at the same time as each livraison of the French version, at least, of de la Sagra’s <tp:taxon-name>Historia</tp:taxon-name> was projected to contain four folio plates accompanied by four sheets of text in octavo (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Stafleu and Cowan 1983</xref>: no. 9150). As early as March–June 1842 there is a published reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Endlicher 1842</xref>: 108; “Belotia <italic>A. Richard Flor. cub. 207. t. 22</italic>”) to the French text of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> and its plate (albeit misnumbered).</p>
            <p>The type of <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> agrees well with the species treated as <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum insigne</tp:taxon-name> (Baill.) Kosterm. in the <italic>Flora Nova–Galiciana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Fryxell 2001</xref>), which has broadly ovate leaf blades with acute apices and a dense and evenly stellate–tomentum below, flowers with sepals and petals ca. 10 mm long, and capsules 16–18 × 24–28 mm. This Mexican species is very distinct from the material of <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name> collected in Cuba, which has ovate leaf blades with acuminate to long acuminate apices and a sparse stellate–tomentum below, flowers with sepals and petals 4–6 mm long, and capsules 8–10 × 10–12 mm. A new combination for the Cuban species of <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name> is necessary as the earliest available epithet belongs to a species of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia</tp:taxon-name>. The name <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum mexicanum</tp:taxon-name>, misapplied to the Cuban species, is here considered to apply to a species endemic to western and southern Mexico that is frequently but incorrectly cited as <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum insigne</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomic summary"><title>Taxonomic summary</title>
        <tp:taxon-treatment>
        <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>                    	
            	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name-part>
            	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">lessertianum</tp:taxon-name-part>
            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77109528-1</object-id>
            </tp:taxon-name>
                <tp:taxon-authority>(Hochr.) Dorr</tp:taxon-authority>
                <tp:taxon-status>comb. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia lessertiana</tp:taxon-name><comment> Hochr., Annuaire Conserv. Jard Bot. Genève 18–19: 90. 1914, as “<tp:taxon-name>Lessertiana</tp:taxon-name>.” <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> var. <italic>lessertiana</italic> (Hochr.) Vict., Contr. Inst. <!--PageBreak-->Bot. Univ. Montréal 63: 13. 1948. TYPE: CUBA. La Havane, s.d. (fl), <tp:taxon-name>Delessert</tp:taxon-name> s.n. (holotype: G-DEL; isotypes: K, NY! [00084148], P). (Basionym)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia caribaea</tp:taxon-name><comment> Sprague, Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 1921(7): 276. 1921. <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum caribaeum</tp:taxon-name> (Sprague) Kosterm., Reinwardtia 6(3): 278. 1962. TYPE: ST. LUCIA, s.d. (fl, fr), <tp:taxon-name>Anderson</tp:taxon-name> s.n. (holotype: K! [K000381875]).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia reticulata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Sprague, Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 1921(7): 277. 1921. <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum reticulatum</tp:taxon-name> (Sprague) Kosterm., Reinwardtia 6(3): 279. 1962. TYPE: NICARAGUA. Chontales, <italic>Seemann 11</italic> (holotype: K).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia campbellii</tp:taxon-name><comment> Sprague, Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 1921(7): 277. 1921, as “<tp:taxon-name>Campbellii</tp:taxon-name>.” TYPE: BELIZE. Seven Hills Estate, s.d. (fl, fr), <italic>E.J.F. Campbell 75</italic> (holotype: K! [K000381880]; isotype: F).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia tabascana</tp:taxon-name><comment> Sprague, Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 1921(7): 278. 1921. <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum tabascanum</tp:taxon-name> (Sprague) Kosterm., Reinwardtia 6(3): 279. 1962. TYPE: MEXICO. Tabasco: Lomas de San Sebastián, 26 Mar 1889 (fl), <italic>Rovirosa 416</italic> (holotype: K; isotypes: F, NY! [00546807], US! [00098426]).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>    
        </tp:nomenclature>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
            <p> Southern Mexico to Costa Rica, and in western Cuba. A collection stated to be from St. Lucia (the type of <tp:taxon-name>Belotia caribaea</tp:taxon-name>) represents either material cultivated in the St. Vincent Botanic Garden or mislabeled material from Cuba (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bornstein 1989: 185–186</xref>).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Note"><title>Note.</title>
            <p> The name <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum grewiifolium</tp:taxon-name> (A. Rich.) Kosterm. is frequently applied to this species, but it is illegitimate because as explained in the text <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> A. Rich. was nomenclaturally superfluous when published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McNeill et al. 2006</xref>: Art. 52.1) and cannot serve as the basionym for this combination. More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rodríguez Fuentes (2000: 32)</xref> accepted <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum grewiifolium</tp:taxon-name> as a new species published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kostermans (1962)</xref> apparently in the belief that Kostermans had explicitly excluded the purported basionym’s type, but this is debatable and in any case <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum grewiifolium</tp:taxon-name> is not a valid name as Kostermans failed to designate a nomenclatural type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McNeill et al. 2006</xref>: Art. 37.1).</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        </tp:taxon-treatment>
        <tp:taxon-treatment>
        <tp:nomenclature>
         		<tp:taxon-name>
         				<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Trichospermum</tp:taxon-name-part>
         				<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mexicanum</tp:taxon-name-part>
         		</tp:taxon-name>
         		<tp:taxon-authority>(DC.)</tp:taxon-authority>
        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum mexicanum</tp:taxon-name><comment> (DC.) Baill., Hist. Pl. 4: 179. 1872 (excluding synonym <tp:taxon-name>Adenodiscus mexicanus</tp:taxon-name> Turcz.). <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> DC., Prodr. 1: 510. 1824. <tp:taxon-name>Belotia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> (DC.) K. Schum. in Engler &amp; Prantl, Nat. Pflanzenfam. 3(6): 28. 1890. <tp:taxon-name>Belotia grewiifolia</tp:taxon-name> A. Rich. in R. de la Sagra, Hist. Phys. Cuba, Pl. Vasc.: 209, t. 21. 1841 [1845], as “<italic>greviæfolia</italic>,” nom. illeg. TYPE: MEXICO. “Nova Hispania,” 1807 (fl), <italic>Lagasca y Segura 86</italic> (holotype: G-DC [IDC microfiche 216!]).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Belotia insignis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Baill., Adansonia 10: 182. 1872. <tp:taxon-name>Trichospermum insigne</tp:taxon-name> (Baill.) Kosterm., Reinwardtia 6(3): 279. 1962, as “<italic>insignis</italic>.” TYPE: MEXICO. “Andes of Mexico,” <italic>Ghiesbreght 356</italic> (holotype: P, photo [F neg. no. 35430] US!; isotype: F).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
        </tp:nomenclature>
        <!--PageBreak-->
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
            <p> Endemic to western and southern Mexico, where it appears to be restricted to the Pacific lowlands and hills from Sinaloa to Oaxaca.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Note"><title>Note.</title>
            <p> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">McVaugh (2000: 526–527)</xref> speculated that the type of <tp:taxon-name>Grewia mexicana</tp:taxon-name> may have been a garden specimen grown at Madrid from Mexican seed contributed by the Expedición Real.</p>
        </tp:treatment-sec>
        </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The comments of two anonymous reviewers were incorporated into this version of the manuscript.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bornstein</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Tiliaceae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Flora of the Lesser Antilles, vol. 5.</source> <publisher-name>Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts: Arnold Arboretum, Harvard University</publisher-name>, <fpage>184</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brizicky</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic and nomenclatural notes on <italic>Zanthoxylum</italic> and <italic>Glycosmis</italic> (Rutaceae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Arnold Arboretum</source> <volume>43</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<article-title/> Contributions to the Flora of Tropical America: XLII. Notes on the genus <italic>Belotia</italic> <source>A. Rich. Bulletin of Miscellaneous Information (Royal Gardens, Kew)</source> <volume>1939</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>517</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4113458" xlink:type="simple">http://www.jstor.org/stable/4113458</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Endlicher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1842</year>)<source> Mantissa botanica sistens generum plantarum, Suppl. 2.</source> <publisher-name>Vindobonae[Vienna], Apud Fridericum Beck</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Dating of the livraisons and volumes of d’Orbigny’s Dictionnaire Universel d’Histoire Naturelle.</article-title> <source>Bishop Museum Occasional Papers</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeussink</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stafleu</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>1979</year>)<source> Index nominum genericorum, vol. 1. Regnum Vegetabile 100.</source> <publisher-name>Scheltema &amp; Holkema</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Utrecht</publisher-loc> &amp; <publisher-loc>Bohn</publisher-loc>, <volume>i–xxvi</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>630</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fryxell</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Tiliaceae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McVaugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Flora Novo–Galiciana</source>, <publisher-name>The University of Michigan Herbarium, Ann Arbor</publisher-name>, vol. <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grisebach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1842</year>)<article-title> Bericht über die Forschungen in der Pflanzen–Geographie während des Jahres 1841.</article-title> <source>Archiv für Naturgeschichte</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>406</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostermans</surname><given-names>AJGH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> The genera <italic>Belotia</italic> Rich. and <italic>Trichospermum</italic> Bl. (Tiliaceae).</article-title> <source>Reinwardtia</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostermans</surname><given-names>AJGH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> A synopsis of the Old World species of <italic>Trichospermum</italic> Blume (Tiliaceae).</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Botanical Society Edinburgh</source> <volume>41</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>430</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McNeill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrie</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdet</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demoulin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawksworth</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marhold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skog</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiersema</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turland</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (Vienna Code) adopted by the Seventeenth International Botanical Congress, Vienna, Austria, July 2005.</article-title> <source>Regnum Vegetabile 146</source>, <publisher-name>A.R.G. Gantner Verlag KG, Ruggell</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Liechtenstein</publisher-loc>, <volume>i–xviii</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McVaugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Botanical results of the Sessé &amp; Mociño Expedition (1787–1803) VII. A guide to relevant scientific names of plants.</source> <publisher-loc>Pittsburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hunt Institute for Botanical Documentation</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1841</year> [1845]) <article-title>Botanique.–Plantes vasculaires. (Essai d’une flore de l’île de Cuba. I).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagra</surname><given-names>R de la</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Histoire physique, politique et naturelle de l’île de Cuba.</source> <publisher-name>Arthus Bertrand</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1842</year> [1845]) <article-title>Bélotie.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Orbigny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Dictionnaire universel d’histoire naturelle</source>, vol. <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>540</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bureau Principal des Éditeurs</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1845</year>)<article-title> Botanica. (Fanerogamia o plantas vasculares).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagra</surname><given-names>R de la</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Historia fisíca, política y natural de la isla de Cuba</source>, vol. <volume>10</volume>. <publisher-name>Arthus Bertrand</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez Fuentes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Tiliaceae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Greuter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Flora de la República de Cuba: Serie A, Plantas Vasculares</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <publisher-loc>Königstein</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Koeltz Scientific Books</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1921</year>)<article-title> A revision of the genus <italic>Belotia</italic>.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Miscellaneous Information (Royal Gardens, Kew)</source> <volume>1921</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4115386" xlink:type="simple">http://www.jstor.org/stable/4115386</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stafleu</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic literature, vol. 3: Lh–O.</article-title> <source>Regnum Vegetabile 105</source>:  <publisher-name>Scheltema and Holkema</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Utrecht: Bohn</publisher-loc>, i–xii, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>980</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stafleu</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic literature, vol. 4: P–Sak.</article-title> <source>Regnum Vegetabile 110</source>: <publisher-name>Scheltema and Holkema</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Utrecht/Antwerpen: Bohn</publisher-loc>, i–ix, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>1214</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>